Guide to the Reinig Company Records 1865-1948
Montana Historical Society Archives
Reinig Company Records
1865-1948
Montana Historical Society, Research Center Archives 225 N. Roberts PO Box 201201 Helena MT 59620-1201 (406) 444-4774 mhslibrary@mt.gov
MC 223
Reinig Company (Helena, Mont.)
8 linear feet of shelf space
The Reinig Company, a Helena, Montana, coffee store and general grocery, was founded by Michael Reinig, a Bavarian emigre in 1865. Reinig also owned a stable, boarding house, and a saloon. The Company operated until 1958. This collection (1865-1948) consists of financial and legal records for the various businesses owned by the Reinig family. Subgroups include M. Reinig / Reinig Company (1874-1943); Brooklyn Bridge Mining and Milling Co. (1907-1909); Ehrenberg and Staff / Ehrenberg and Reinig / Montana Cycle Co.(1894-1896); Harmonia Gesang Verein (1873-1877); Helena Cab Co. / Merchants Delivery (1908-1923); and various family members. [OVERSIZE MATERIAL: map case].
Michael Reinig, founder of the Reinig Company, was born in Deidesheim, Bavaria, on March 31, 1835, the son of Jacob and Frances Reinig. He learned the baker's trade in his home town and then as a young man left for New York, where he joined an expedition heading for California by way of Havana and the Isthmus of Panama. From California, Reinig traveled to Oregon and Washington. In 1865 he left The Dalles, Oregon, and traveled to Helena, Montana Territory, by way of Spokane and Deer Lodge. He almost immediately went to work for the San Francisco Bakery on State Street and a few months later bought the business. He gradually expanded the operation to include a boarding house and a grocery on the corner of State and Joliet Streets, and eventually added a stable on Warren Street, a coffee business, and a saloon in East Helena. In 1904 Michael decided to take a trip to visit his birthplace in Germany. As part of his preparations he incorporated as the Reinig Company. Management of the company was given to William C. Bardon, who also continued to operate the company after Reinig's death. The store ceased business c. 1958.
In 1869, Michael Reinig married Matilda, a Norwegian native who had come to the United States at age three and had moved to Helena in 1868. They had a son Charles N. Raunig (b.1871) and a daughter Anna (b.1873). Michael was a Mason and was active with the Harmonia Gesang Verein, a German club in Helena. Michael Reinig died September 19, 1909, and Matilda Reinig died June 23, 1934.
Their son Charles N. Reinig was born March 22, 1871. He studied dentistry in Pennsylvania and then practiced in Latin America for several years. He returned to Helena in the mid-1890s and became a partner with Gus Ehrenberg in the Montana Cycle Company and clerked in his father's store until 1900 when he moved to Seattle. After Michael Reinig's death Charles N. Reinig served as president of the company until 1935, but continued to reside in Seattle. He died September 29, 1958, in Winslow, Washington.
William C. Bardon was born in Florrisant, Missouri, June 2, 1870. He moved to Helena in 1889 and went to work as a delivery boy for the Reinig grocery. He gradually rose in the business until he took over management of the store in 1900. He continued to serve as vice-president and manager after Mike Reinig's death in 1909. He became president after Charles N. Reinig resigned in 1935. Bardon, along with other Helena merchants, formed the Merchants Delivery Company as a cooperative arrangement to share delivery services. On September 11, 1907, William married Anna, daughter of Michael and Matilda Reinig. William Bardon died January 24, 1955, and less than four months later his wife Anna died on May 17, 1955.
William Eicke was born in Leibnau, Hanover, Germany in 1828. At the age of 18 he moved to Baltimore, Maryland, and worked as a baker. There he married and had one son. In the Civil War he refused to join the Confederate forces and was imprisoned in Richmond. He bribed his way out and left for California. Leaving his wife and infant son there he joined Michael Reinig at The Dalles, Oregon, and later in Helena. In California his wife heard that he had been killed by Indians at The Dalles and remarried. Eicke worked for the Reinig store and lived with the Reinigs for forty years. He died June 1, 1911.
Content Description:
This collection contains subgroups for various businesses owned by the Reinig Family and for various family members and associates.
M. Reinig / Reinig Company grocery business records include general correspondence (1890-1943); financial records (1870-1948), including account ledgers, cash books, invoices, trial balances, etc.; legal documents (1879-1890); a subject file (1934-1935) concerning New Deal coffee codes; miscellany (1900-1913, n.d.), including architect's drawings and specifications for the store, membership lists for the Helena Retail Merchants' Exchange, etc.; and a clipping (1935) about the history of the store.
Brooklyn Bridge Mining and Milling Company records include general correspondence (1908) of John Kreuger about refinancing of the company; legal documents (1909); and organizational materials (1907-1908), including stockholder lists.
Ehrenberg and Staff / Ehrenberg and Reinig / Montana Cycle Company records include incoming correspondence (1894-1895) with bicycle manufacturers and suppliers, and financial records (1894-1896) consisting mostly of invoices.
Harmonia Gesang Verein records consist of financial records (1873-1877).
Helena Cab Company / Merchants Delivery Company records consist of general correspondence (1909-1917) including answers to a questionaire about the delivery service from merchants in Champaign, Illinois; financial records (1911-1924); legal documents (1908-1914); and organizational records (1909-1923).
Michael Reinig's personal papers consist of incoming correspondence (1892-1908) mostly about his orchard property near San Diego, California; financial records (1893-1909); legal documents (1873-1906); and miscellany (1895-1909).
In addition there are small subgroups of papers for Charles N. Reinig, Matilida Reinig, William Reinig, Anna Reinig Bardon, William C. Bardon, and William Eicke. [OVERSIZE MATERIAL: map case]
Arrangement:
by series
Acquisition Information:
available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Coffee trade
Dentistry
German Americans
Grocery trade
Mines and mineral resources--Montana--Lewis and Clark County
Stables
Argenta (Mont.)
Argentina
Brazil
East Helena (Mont.)--Commerce
Helena (Mont.)--Commerce
Helena (Mont.)--Industries
Otay (Calif.)
San Diego (Calif.)
Montana
Business, Industry, and Labor
German Americans
Mines and Mineral Resources
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- M. Reinig / Reinig Company
    - (Box-folder /)
  - General Correspondence
    - A-Z, 1890 (Box-folder 1 / 1-4)
    - B-Z, 1895 (Box-folder 1 / 5-8)
    - Miscellaneous, 1911,1917, 1937-1943 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
  - Financial Records
    - Account Ledger ("journal"), Jan.1915- Mar.1917 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
    - Account ledger, July 1917- Dec.1918, Aug.1920- Dec.1921 (Volume Vol. 1)
    - Account ledger: coffee, 1920-1933 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
    - Account ledger ("Country bills"), Apr.1912- Mar.1917 (Volume Vol. 2)
    - Annual financial report, 1912-1914 (Box-folder 2 / 2)
    - Balance sheets, 1895-1896 (Box-folder OVBX /)
    - Assets and liabilities, financial statements, etc., 1880, 1909-1916 (Box-folder 2 / 3)
    - Bank books (11 books), 1892-1909 (Box-folder 2 / 4-7)
    - Canceled checks, Jan.-Feb. 1909 (Box-folder 2 / 8)
    - Canceled checks, Jan.-Mar. 1914 (Box-folder 2 / 9)
    - Canceled checks, June-Aug. 1914 (Box-folder 2 / 10)
    - Canceled checks, Dec.1915- Jan.1916 (Box-folder 2 / 11)
    - Cash book, 1900 (Box-folder 3 / 1)
    - Cash book, 1914-1915 (Box-folder 3 / 2)
    - Cash books, 1916-1918 (Volume Vol. 3-5)
    - Cash book ("journal"), Jan.1919- June 1920 (Volume Vol. 6)
    - Cash book, June-Oct. 1922 (Volume Vol. 7)
    - Cash book, Oct.1922- Oct.1924 (Box-folder 3 / 3)
    - Cash books ("Journal"), Oct.1924- May 1930 (Box-folder 4 / 1-3)
    - Cash books, July 1935- Nov.1937 (Box-folder 4 / 4-5)
    - Cash books, Nov.1937- Oct.1940 (Box-folder 5 / 1-3)
    - Cash book, May 1942- Apr.1944 (Box-folder 5 / 4)
    - Cash book, May 1945- Sept. 1948 (Box-folder 5 / 5)
    - Cash journal, 1916-1917 (Volume Vol. 8)
    - Cash received on account ("Cash blotter"), Jan.1906- Feb.1907 (Box-folder 5 / 6)
    - Cash received on account, June 1914- Apr. 1915 (Box-folder 5 / 7)
    - Check stubs, Mar.-Apr. 1913 (Box-folder 6 / 1)
    - Closing journal entries and trial balance, loss and gain statements, 1912-1923 (Box-folder 6 / 2)
    - Collections (2 books), 1891, 1896-1897 (Box-folder 6 / 3)
    - Daybook, July 2-22, 1870 (Box-folder 6 / 4)
    - Daybook, Apr.-Aug. 1894 (Box-folder 6 / 5)
    - Daybook: Unionville, Feb-Aug. 1874 (Box-folder 6 / 6)
    - General journals, 1903-1909 (Box-folder OVBX /)
    - General Ledger, 1903 (Box-folder 6 / 7)
    - General ledger, 1904-1911 (Volume Vol. 9)
    - General ledger, 1911-1915 (Box-folder 7 / 1)
    - General ledger, 1916-1928 (Volume Vol. 10)
    - Insurance policies, 1924-1926 (Box-folder 7 / 2)
    - Insurance policies: East Helena lodging house, 1893 (Box-folder 7 / 3)
    - Insurance policies: East Helena saloon, 1902-1908 (Box-folder 7 / 4)
    - State Street store, 1897-1908, 1923-1924 (Box-folder 7 / 5)
    - Insurance policies: State Street store merchandise, 1897-1909, 1924-1925 (Box-folder 7 / 6)
    - Insurance policies: Warren Street stable, 1902-1908, 1923-1925 (Box-folder 7 / 7)
    - Insurance receipts for goods shipped on Missouri River steamers, 1881 (Box-folder 7 / 8)
    - Insurance record, 1894-1914 (Box-folder 7 / 9)
    - Invoice: M. Reinig San Francisco Bakery, 1879 (Box-folder 7 / 10)
    - Invoices: A-E (includes Auerbach & Weigel; Bach, Cory & Co.; Benson, Carpenter & Co.; Central Meat Market; T.H. Clewell; et al.), 1894-1897 (Box-folder 7 / 11)
    - Invoices: F-H (includes August Fack; C. Ferree; Fister & Co.; Wm. Fowler; Charles Grossman; Helena Ice Co.; Helena Power and Light Co.; et al.), 1894-1897 (Box-folder 7 / 12)
    - Invoices: I-M (includes Nick Kessler; Kleinschmidt & Bro.; F.S. Lang; H. Lindner; Montana Lumber & Manufacturing Co.; Montana Produce and Commission Co.; et al.), 1894-1897 (Box-folder 7 / 13)
    - Invoices: N-P (includes New York Dry Good Co.; F.J. Nye; Parchen Drug Co.; Jacob Post; T.C. Power & Co.; et al.), 1894-1897 (Box-folder 7 / 14)
    - Invoices: R-S (includes Raleigh & Clarke; Rocky Mountain Bell Telephone Co.; Sanford & Evans; A.E. Shaw; Emil Starz; Steele, Hindson & Co.; J. Switzer; et al.), 1894-1897 (Box-folder 8 / 1)
    - Invoices: T-Y (includes H.S. Thurber & Co.; Turner & Co.; Union Mercantile Co.; Weisenhorn Carriage Manufacturing Co.; C.K. Wells Co.; et al), 1894-1897 (Box-folder 8 / 2)
    - Invoices: A-L, 1917 (Box-folder 8 / 3)
    - Invoices: M-Y, 1917 (Box-folder 8 / 4)
    - Journal, 1910-1914 (Volume Vol. 11)
    - Ledger index (Box-folder 8 / 5)
    - Morris Audit Company, n.d. (Box-folder 8 / 6)
    - Promisory notes, 1881-1889 (Box-folder 8 / 7)
    - Promisory notes, 1890-1909 (Box-folder 8 / 8)
    - Receipt copy book, Dec.1912- July 1913 (Box-folder 8 / 9)
    - Receipt copy book, Jan.-Nov. 1914 (Box-folder 8 / 10)
    - Receipts, 1894-1897, 1907 (Box-folder 8 / 11)
    - Receipts: hay scales, 1895-1896 (Box-folder 8 / 12)
    - Remittance accounts, 1913-1917 (Box-folder 8 / 13)
    - Remittance book ("Telegrams")), Apr.1897- Dec.1907 (Box-folder 8 / 14)
    - Sales records, 1916-1921, 1919-1926 (Volume Vol. 12-13)
    - Sales record ("Book 5"), July 1931- Sept.1937 (Box-folder 9 / 1)
    - Sale record ("Cash"), Sept.1937- Aug.1939 (Box-folder 9 / 2)
    - Sight drafts, etc., 1894-1897 (Box-folder 9 / 3)
    - Taxes, 1905-1913, 1916-1920 (Box-folder 9 / 4-5)
    - Trial balance book, 1895-1921 (Volume Vol. 14)
  - Legal Documents
    - Miscellaneous (re bakery and butcher shop), 1879-1890 (Box-folder OVBX /)
  - Photographs
    - "Historic picture of Helena, Montana, taken spring of 1865" (Reinig stores marked with x's; draft of letter of condolence in French on back) (Box-folder 9 / 6)
  - Printed Materials
    - List of printed material transferred to Library, n.d. (Box-folder 9 / 7)
  - Subject Files
    - Coffee code (correspondence), 1934-1935 (Box-folder 9 / 8)
    - Coffee code (bulletins), 1934-1935 (Box-folder 9 / 9)
    - Coffee code (special bulletins and replacement quotations bulletins), 1934-1935 (Box-folder 9 / 10)
    - Coffee code (miscellaneous), 1934-1935 (Box-folder 9 / 11)
  - Miscellany
    - Advertising circulars, 1930s (Box-folder 9 / 12)
    - Architect's drawings of Reinig Company store [OVERSIZE MATERIAL: Map Case], n.d. (Box-folder OVFD /)
    - "Gaskell's Complete Compendium of elegan Ssriting" sample sheet (Box-folder OVBX /)
    - Helena Retail Merchants' Exchange membership list, Jan.1913, n.d. (Box-folder 9 / 13-14)
    - List of artifacts transferred to Museum (Box-folder 9 / 15)
    - Specifications for building of store, n.d. (Box-folder 9 / 16)
    - Specifications for East Helena store, 1900 (Box-folder 9 / 17)
    - Unidentified list, by town, of married women in Lewis and Clark, Broadwater, Gallatin, Jefferson, Madison, Meagher, and Powell counties (Box-folder 9 / 18)
  - Clippings
    - "Reinig Company grocery store, oldest of its kind in state, has its 70th anniversary", 1935 (Box-folder 9 / 19)
- Brooklyn Bridge Mining And Milling Company
  - General Correspondence
    - John Krueger (re stock re-issue), Aug.-Dec. 1908 (Box-folder 10 / 1)
  - Legal Documents
    - Agreements and deeds re Lone Star quartz lode claim, Lewis and Clark County, 1909 (Box-folder 10 / 2)
  - Organization
    - Stock re-issues, 1907-1908 (Box-folder 10 / 3)
    - Stockholder lists, n.d. (Box-folder 10 / 4)
- Ehrenberg and Staff / Ehrenberg and Reinig / Montana Cycle Co.
  - Incoming Correspondence
    - Ariel Cycle Manufacturing Co., 1894-1895 (Box-folder 10 / 5)
    - Miscellaneous (includes Hales & Anderson, B.F. Goodrich Co., Indianapolis Rubber Co., Meteor Cycle Manufacturing Co., Morgan & Wright, 1894-1895 (Box-folder 10 / 6)
  - Financial Records
    - Canceled checks and checkstubs, 1896 (Box-folder 10 / 7)
    - Invoices: Ariel Cycle Manufacturing Co., 1894-1895, 1896 (Box-folder 10 / 8-9)
    - Invoices: B-W (includes Buffalo Wheel Co., Von Lenerke & Antoine, et al.), 1894-1896 (Box-folder 10 / 10)
    - Promissory notes, 1896 (Box-folder 10 / 11)
    - Receipts, 1894-1895 (Box-folder 10 / 12)
  - Legal Documents
    - Agreement: Ariel Cycle Manufacturing Co., 1896 (Box-folder 10 / 13)
  - Miscellany
    - Warrany certificate, 1894 (Box-folder 10 / 14)
- Harmonia Gesang Verein
  - Financial Records
    - Account books (2 books), 1873-1874 (Box-folder 10 / 15)
    - Invoices, etc., 1874-1877 (Box-folder 10 / 16)
- Helena Cab Company / Merchants Delivery Company
  - General Correspondence
    - G-R (includes answers to questionaire on the company from merchants in Champaign, Illinois), 1909-1917 (Box-folder 10 / 17)
    - Miscellaneous (re sale of property), Jan-Mar 1923 (Box-folder 10 / 18)
  - Financial Records
    - Daybook, Aug. 1908-July 1910 (Box-folder 10 / 19)
    - Taxes, receipts, etc., 1911,1914, 1924 (Box-folder 10 / 20)
  - Legal Documents
    - Miscellaneous, 1908-1914 (Box-folder 10 / 21)
  - Organization
    - Directors' minutes authorizing sale of property to W.C. Bardon, Feb.12, 1923 (Box-folder 10 / 22)
    - Stock certificates; list of stockholders, 1909-1915, 1922 (Box-folder 10 / 23)
    - Stockholders' minutes authorizing sale of property to Merchants Delivery Company, Aug.2, 1910 (Box-folder 10 / 24)
- Michael Reinig
  - Incoming Correspondence
    - N.W. Downs (re Otay, California, orchard), 1894-1895 (Box-folder 11 / 1)
    - Miscellaneous [in German], 1893-1895 (Box-folder 11 / 2)
    - Miscellaneous (re San Diego property, life insurance, trip to Germany, etc.), 1892-1908 (Box-folder 11 / 3)
    - Letters of introduction, 1876 (Box-folder 11 / 4)
  - General Correspondence
    - Telegrams (re San Diego property), 1892, 1895 (Box-folder 11 / 5)
  - Financial Records
    - Insurance policies, 1903-1909 (Box-folder 11 / 6)
    - Invoices, 1893-1897 (Box-folder 11 / 7)
    - Stock certificates, 1889-1895 (Box-folder 11 / 8)
    - Taxes, 1893-1909 (Box-folder 11 / 9)
    - Miscellaneous (includes canceled checks, bullion deposit receipt, lodge dues), 1894,1896 (Box-folder 11 / 10)
  - Legal Documents
    - Agreements, 1879-1906 (Box-folder 11 / 11)
    - Deeds, 1866-1902 (Box-folder 11 / 12)
    - Mineral certificate, 1875 (Box-folder OVBX /)
    - Quartz location: Sampson Lode, 1899 (Box-folder 11 / 13)
    - San Diego County land deeds, 1892-1913 (Box-folder 11 / 14)
  - Miscellany
    - Application for degree of Knight Rose Croix, n.d. (Box-folder 11 / 15)
    - Deeds etc. of other parties, 1873-1893 (Box-folder 11 / 16)
    - List of property transfers, n.d. (Box-folder 11 / 17)
    - Masonic initiation certificate, 1904 (Box-folder OVBX /)
    - Membership cards, business cards, programs, etc., 1906-1909, n.d. (Box-folder 11 / 18)
    - Plats of San Diego land [OVERSIZE MATERIAL: Map Case] (Box-folder OVFD /)
  - Clippings
    - Miscellaneous [in German], 1895 (Box-folder 11 / 19)
- C.n. Reinig
  - General Correspondence
    - N.W. Downs (re Otay, California, orchard), 1893-1894 (Box-folder 11 / 20)
    - Miscellaneous (re Otay, California, property; death of Michael Reinig), 1889,1893, 1909 (Box-folder 11 / 21)
  - Outgoing Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous (re dentistry in Brazil and Argentina, sale of property), 1889,1893 (Box-folder 11 / 22)
  - Financial Records
    - Invoices, etc., 1889, 1893-1896 (Box-folder 11 / 23)
    - Taxes, 1909 (Box-folder 11 / 24)
  - Writings and Speeches
    - Reminiscence of residence in Argentina, and travel in Germany (also drafts of homecoming speeches), 1905 (Box-folder 11 / 25)
  - Miscellany
    - Helena Business College attendance records, business card, 1886,1904 (Box-folder 11 / 26)
    - Philadelphia Dental College Certificate [OVERSIZE MATERIAL: Map Case], 1898-1899 (Box-folder OVFD /)
  - Clippings
    - Scrap book, 1901 (Box-folder 11 / 27)
- Matilda Reinig
  - Financial Records
    - Insurance policies, 1907-1922 (Box-folder 11 / 28)
    - Taxes, 1899-1909 (Box-folder 11 / 29)
  - Legal Documents
    - Miscellaneous, 1896,1913 (Box-folder 11 / 30)
- William W. Reinig
  - Legal Documents
    - Invoices, etc., 1894-1893 (Box-folder 11 / 31)
    - Option on Crystal placer claim, 1896 (Box-folder 11 / 32)
- Anna Reinig Bardon
  - Incoming Correspondence
    - "Adele" to Anna Bardon, 1907 (Box-folder 12 / 1)
  - Outgoing Correspondence
    - "Bill's history" (re William Eicke), 1910,1911 (Box-folder 12 / 2)
  - Photographs
    - List of photographs transferred to Photo Archives (Box-folder 12 / 3)
- William C. Bardon
  - Incoming Correspondence
    - Philip Hartung (re death of Michael Reinig), 1909 (Box-folder 12 / 4)
    - Miscellaneous (includes H.R. Comley; Marguerite Theodore; Associated Pharmacists; Texas Coastal Oil Co.; Oregon Land and Timber Co.), 1912-1924 (Box-folder 12 / 5)
    - Miscellaneous (in German), 1910-1911 (Box-folder 12 / 6)
  - General Correspondence
    - Elizabeth E. Holcomb, 1940-1943 (Box-folder 12 / 7)
  - Financial Records
    - Associated Pharmacists receipts, stock certificates, 1916 (Box-folder 12 / 8)
    - Insurance policies, 1922-1926 (Box-folder 12 / 9)
    - Taxes, 1893, 1909-1918 (Box-folder 12 / 10)
  - Legal Documents
    - A-B-C Mining Company, 1928 (Box-folder 12 / 11)
    - Agreements, 1917,1938 (Box-folder 12 / 12)
  - Miscellany
    - Christmas cards, memberships, etc., 1893-1895, 1916,n.d. (Box-folder 12 / 13)
- William Eicke
  - Court Papers
    - Application for citizenship, 1894 (Box-folder 12 / 14)
  - Financial Records
    - Receipts, taxes, 1895-1906 (Box-folder 12 / 15)
  - Legal Documents
    - Deeds, 1880-1885, 1907 (Box-folder 12 / 16)